<tool id="SAFT" name="SAFT" version="0.2">
  <description>Simple Alignment Filtering Tool</description>
  <requirements>
	<requirement type="package" version="0.1">oqtans</requirement>
  </requirements>
  <command interpreter="bash">
     ./optimal_filter_set_galaxy.sh $anno_input_selected $bam_alignments $best_score $score_matrix $Filtered_Alignment 
     >> $Log_File
  </command>

  <inputs>
	<param format="gff3" name="anno_input_selected" type="data" label="Genome annotation in GFF3 format" help="Partial genome annotation in GFF3 format describing the known gene structures for the provided genome."/>
    <param format="bam" name="bam_alignments" type="data" label="BAM alignment file" help="Alignment file in BAM format."/>
  </inputs>

  <outputs>
    <data format="bam" name="Filtered_Alignment" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string}: Optimally filtered"/>
    <data format="txt" name="best_score" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string}: Best Scorings"/>
    <data format="txt" name="score_matrix" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string}: Evaluated Filter Combinations"/>
    <data format="txt" name="Log_File" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string}: log file"/>
  </outputs>

  <help>

.. class:: infomark

**What it does** 

`SAFT` optimizes filtering criteria for a given alignemnt in BAM format.
The filtering is optimized to produce an alignment set with maximal intron
accuracy, measured on a given annotation in GFF format.

**Inputs**

`SAFT` requires two input files to run:

1. Annotation file either in GFF3, containing the necessary information about the transcripts that are used for accuracy estimation.
2. The BAM alignment file, which stores the read alignments in a compressed format. It can be generated using the `SAM-to-BAM` tool in the NGS: SAM Tools section.

**Output**

`SAFT` generates four different output files:

1. The best score showing the most sensitive, the most precise, and the best trade of filter in the first, second, and third line, respectively.
2. The score matrix containing the performances of every single tested filtering combination.
3. An optimally filtered alignment set. 
4. The log file summarizing the run.

------

**Licenses**

If **SAFT** is used to obtain results for scientific publications it
should be cited as [1]_ .

**References** 

.. [1] Kahles, A, Bohnert, R, Behr, J, and Rätsch, G (2013): SAFT: Simple Alignment Filtering Tool. in Preparation.

------

.. class:: infomark

**About formats**

**GFF3 format** General Feature Format is a format for describing genes
and other features associated with DNA, RNA and protein
sequences. GFF3 lines have nine tab-separated fields:

1. seqid - The name of a chromosome or scaffold.
2. source - The program that generated this feature.
3. type - The name of this type of feature. Some examples of standard feature types are "gene", "CDS", "protein", "mRNA", and "exon". 
4. start - The starting position of the feature in the sequence. The first base is numbered 1.
5. stop - The ending position of the feature (inclusive).
6. score - A score between 0 and 1000. If there is no score value, enter ".".
7. strand - Valid entries include '+', '-', or '.' (for don't know/care).
8. phase - If the feature is a coding exon, frame should be a number between 0-2 that represents the reading frame of the first base. If the feature is not a coding exon, the value should be '.'.
9. attributes - All lines with the same group are linked together into a single item.

For more information see http://www.sequenceontology.org/gff3.shtml

**SAM/BAM format** The Sequence Alignment/Map (SAM) format is a
tab-limited text format that stores large nucleotide sequence
alignments. BAM is the binary version of a SAM file that allows for
fast and intensive data processing. The format specification and the
description of SAMtools can be found on
http://samtools.sourceforge.net/.

------

Version 0.2 (Sept. 2013)

</help>
</tool>
