<tool id="readstats" name="ReadStats" version="2.2">
  <description>Outputs a statistic about the read alignments and the coverage of the genes.</description>
  <requirements>
	<requirement type="package" version="0.1">oqtans</requirement>
  </requirements>
  <command interpreter="bash">
    ../src/./read_stats.sh $gff_input $bam_alignments $read_stats_out $read_stats_out.extra_files_path
    >> $Log_File
  </command>
  
  <inputs>
    <param format="gff3" name="gff_input" type="data" label="Genome annotation in GFF3 format" help="Partial genome annotation in GFF3 format describing the known gene structures for the provided genome."/>
    <param format="bam" name="bam_alignments" type="data" label="BAM alignment file" help="BAM alignment file. Can be generated from SAM files using the SAM Tools."/>
  </inputs>

  <outputs>
    <data format="txt" name="read_stats_out" label="Read statistic"/>
    <data format="txt" name="Log_File" label="Read statistics Log File"/>
  </outputs>

  <tests>
    <test>
      <!--
	command:
	./read_stats.sh ../test_data/rquant_nGASP-Train-I.gff3 ../test_data/rquant_nGASP-Train-I.bam ../test_data/rquant_nGASP-Train-I_read_stats.txt ../test_data
	-->
      <param name="gff_input" value="rquant_nGASP-Train-I.gff3" ftype="gff3" />
      <param name="bam_alignments" value="rquant_nGASP-Train-I.bam" ftype="bam" />
      <output name="rquant_out" file="rquant_nGASP-Train-I_read_stats.txt" label="Read Statistics"/>
    </test>
  </tests>

  <help>

.. class:: infomark

**What it does** 

`ReadStats` generates a statistic about the read alignments (number of reads) and the covered genes (read coverage, number of covered introns, intron coverage). It can be used to perform a sanity check of the read alignments file and the annotation.

**Inputs**

`ReadStats` requires three input files to run:

1. The Genome Information Object, containing essential information about the genome (sequence, size, etc). It can be created using the `GenomeTool` from a fasta file.
2. The Genome Annotation Object, containing the necessary information about the transcripts that are to be quantified. It can be constructed using the `GFF2Anno` tool from an annotation in GFF3 format.
3. The BAM alignment file, which stores the read alignments in a compressed format. It can be generated using the `SAM-to-BAM` tool in the NGS: SAM Tools section.


**Output**

`ReadStats` writes an output file (Read Statistic) containing

1. the number of reads,
2. the read coverage of the given genes,
3. the number of covered introns, and
4. the intron coverage.

------

.. class:: infomark

**About formats**

**GFF3 format** General Feature Format is a format for describing genes
and other features associated with DNA, RNA and protein
sequences. GFF3 lines have nine tab-separated fields:

1. seqid - The name of a chromosome or scaffold.
2. source - The program that generated this feature.
3. type - The name of this type of feature. Some examples of standard feature types are "gene", "CDS", "protein", "mRNA", and "exon". 
4. start - The starting position of the feature in the sequence. The first base is numbered 1.
5. stop - The ending position of the feature (inclusive).
6. score - A score between 0 and 1000. If there is no score value, enter ".".
7. strand - Valid entries include '+', '-', or '.' (for don't know/care).
8. phase - If the feature is a coding exon, frame should be a number between 0-2 that represents the reading frame of the first base. If the feature is not a coding exon, the value should be '.'.
9. attributes - All lines with the same group are linked together into a single item.

For more information see http://www.sequenceontology.org/gff3.shtml

**SAM/BAM format** The Sequence Alignment/Map (SAM) format is a
tab-limited text format that stores large nucleotide sequence
alignments. BAM is the binary version of a SAM file that allows for
fast and intensive data processing. The format specification and the
description of SAMtools can be found on
http://samtools.sourceforge.net/.

------

Version 2.1 (August 2011)

</help>
</tool>
