<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tool id="kirmes_motifscanner" name="(2) Prepare Prediction Dataset" version="0.8">
  <description>Find a set of motifs in a FASTA file</description>
  <requirements>
	<requirement type='package'>kirmes</requirement>
  </requirements>
  <command interpreter="python">
    ../src/kmotif.py -t kiml -p $positives -i $pgff -x $imm -n $negatives -j $ngff 
  </command>
  <inputs>
    <param name="imm" type="data" format="imm"  
      help="INCLUSive Motif Model file with motifs to be found in FASTAs">
      <label>Motifs as position weight matrices</label>
    </param>
    <param format="fasta" name="positives" type="data"
      label="Sequences in which to look for motifs" 
      help="Necessary if you want to run a KIRMES prediction on this data set" />
    <param format="fasta" name="negatives" type="data"
      label="Optional second set in which to look for motifs" optional="True"
      help="" />
  </inputs>
  <outputs>
    <data format="gff" name="pgff" label="INCLUSive Motif Positions (from 1st FASTA)"/>
    <data format="gff" name="ngff" label="INCLUSive Motif Positions (from 2nd FASTA)"/>
  </outputs>
  <help>

.. class:: infomark

**Introduction**

This is KIRMES: Kernel-based Identification of Regulatory Modules
in Euchromatic Sequences. KIRMES predicts coregulation based on
gene sets that exhibit similar behavior. 

You can upload a pair of FASTA files, containing the regulatory region
of genes e.g. from a microarray experiment, ChIP-chip binding or 
next generation sequencing data. A comparison to common motif finding 
methods and data about its effectiveness has been published in [1].

The following is a description of the Motif Finding, Training and 
Prediction tools found on this web server.

If you have additional questions about KIRMES, please write an
email to sebi@tue.mpg.de. For problems with our Galaxy server, please 
write to galaxy@raetschlab.org

For a general introduction to Galaxy, please visit 
http://galaxy.psu.edu/

------

.. class:: infomark

**1. Motif Finders** 

In a first step, KIRMES identifies the "interesting" areas of the 
regulatory regions in the input data, using common motif finding algorithms.
You can choose between a simple k-mer counting strategy (fastest), the INCLUSive
MotifSampler developed by Gert Thijs et al. [2], and PRIORITY, a state-of-the-art
Gibbs sampler, developed by Raluca Gordan et al. [3]. These programs return a list of 
50-200 motifs and their best-matching location in each entry of the FASTA file. 

*This is the INCLUSive MotifScanner tool [2]*

If you want to use a trained classifier to predict classes on a dataset, you also need to perform
the motif finding step on this data. This tool helps you to look for the exact same
motifs in your evaluation dataset as the ones in the training dataset. To this end, 
you have to provide this tool with the prediction dataset, and with the original motif 
model file you obtained from the initial motif finding step. The matrix or model file
is returned by these tools along with the positions. This scanning tool only uses the
already established motifs and looks for their occurrence in the supplied FASTA file.

Matrix files have to be in IMM format, or INCLUSive Motif Model format. It may consist
of several matrices in one file. Please see the Examples and Instructions tool for an
example file in IMM format.

**References** 

[1] Schultheiss SJ, Busch W, Lohmann JU, Kohlbacher O, Raetsch G. 
(2009) KIRMES: Kernel-based identification of regulatory modules in 
euchromatic sequences. Bioinformatics 25(16):2126-33.

[2] Thijs G, Moreau Y, De Smet F, Mathys J, Lescot M, Rombauts S, Rouze P, 
De Moor B, Marchal K. (2002) INCLUSive: integrated clustering, upstream 
sequence retrieval and motif sampling. Bioinformatics 18(2):331-332.

[3] Gordan R, Narlikar L, Hartemink AJ. (2008) A fast, alignment-free, 
conservation-based method for transcription factor binding site discovery.
Lecture Notes in Computer Science: RECOMB 2008, Vingron M and Wong L, Eds.
Springer Verlag Heidelberg, Germany. 4955:98-111.




------

.. class:: infomark

**Licence Information: GPL**


Copyright (C) Sebastian J. Schultheiss (sebi@umich.edu)                           
                                                                                             
This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify                   
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by                   
the Free Software Foundation; either version 3 of the License, or                      
(at your option) any later version.                                                    
                                                                                             
This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,                        
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of                         
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the                            
GNU General Public License for more details.                                           
                                                                                             
You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License                       
along with this program; if not, see http://www.gnu.org/licenses                       
or write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street,                    
Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301  USA                                                

  </help>
</tool>
